<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The bloody proiect, or a discovery of the new designe, in the present war. Being a perfect narrative of the present proceedings of the severall grandee factions, for the prevention of a just peace, and promoting of a causelesse warre, to the destruction of the King, Parliament &amp; people. Whereunto is annexed several expedients for an happy accommodation tending to the satisfaction of all parties, without the further effusion of blood. / By W.P. Gent.</title>
            <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97094</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W681</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E460_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3843</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872505</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872505</idno>
            <idno type="VID">162129</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97094)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162129)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 73:E460[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The bloody proiect, or a discovery of the new designe, in the present war. Being a perfect narrative of the present proceedings of the severall grandee factions, for the prevention of a just peace, and promoting of a causelesse warre, to the destruction of the King, Parliament &amp; people. Whereunto is annexed several expedients for an happy accommodation tending to the satisfaction of all parties, without the further effusion of blood. / By W.P. Gent.</title>
                  <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in this yeare of dissembling, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W.P. = William Walwyn.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug. ye 21".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Peace --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:162129:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Bloody Proiect, Or a diſcovery of the New <hi>Deſigne,</hi> in the preſent War.</p>
            <p>BEING A perfect Narrative of the preſent proceedings of the ſeverall Grandee Factions, for the prevention of a <hi>juſt Peace,</hi> and promoting of a <hi>cauſeleſſe Warre,</hi> to the deſtruction of THE KING, PARLIAMENT &amp; PEOPLE.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed Several Expedients for an happy Accommodation tending to the ſatisfaction of all Parties, without the further effuſion of blood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By W. P.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>Printed in this Yeare of diſſembling, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:162129:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:162129:2"/>
            <head>The Bloody Project. <hi>OR</hi> New deſign in the preſent War diſcovered.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N all undertakings, which may occaſion war or bloodſhed, men have great need to be ſure that their cauſe be right, both in reſpect of themſelves and others: for if they kill men themſelves, or cauſe others to kill, without a juſt cauſe, and upon the extreameſt neceſſity, they not only diſturbe the peace of men, and familyes, and bring miſery and poverty upon a Nation, but are indeed abſolute murtherers.</p>
            <p>Nor will it in any meaſure ſatisfy the Conſcience, or <hi>Gods juſtice,</hi> to go on in uncertainties, for in doubtfull caſes men ought to ſtand ſtill, and conſider, untill certainty do appear, eſpecially when killing and ſleying of men (the moſt horrid worke to <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Scripture</hi>) is in queſtion.</p>
            <p>Far be it from any man haſtily to engage in any undertaking, which may occaſion a War, before the <hi>cauſe</hi> he is to fight for, be <hi>rightly, and plainly ſtated, well conſidered, and throughly underſtood to be juſt, and of</hi> abſolute neceſſity <hi>to be maintained;</hi> nothing being more abom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nable in the ſight of God or good men, then ſuch perſons who <hi>run<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e out to ſhed blood</hi> for money, or to ſupport this or the other <hi>Intereſt,</hi> but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſider the <hi>cauſe</hi> for which they engage, nor ought el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, but <hi>pay, intereſt, honour, &amp;c.</hi> ſuch are they who ſo eagerly endeavour to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the intereſt of a <hi>King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> by the deſtruction of the <hi>Peoples Intereſt,</hi> the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Scots</hi> againſt the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Independents,</hi> by the ruine of the <hi>Presbyterians<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and becauſe it beſt conſiſts with their preſent <hi>honour, profit</hi> or <hi>humours,</hi> make it their buſines to <hi>pick quarrels,</hi> and <hi>encreaſe diviſions</hi> and <hi>jealouſies,</hi> that ſo they may fiſh in the waters which they themſelves have <hi>troubled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let ſuch know, who ever they be, that though they may and do for a while brave it out, and flouriſh, yet a time is comming, and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:162129:3"/>on apace, when for all the <hi>murthers</hi> they have cauſed, and miſchiefs they have committed, <hi>they ſhall come to judgement,</hi> and then their <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences</hi> will be as a thouſand witneſſes againſt them.</p>
            <p>But eſpecially let men pretending conſcience take heed how they ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther engage themſelves, or perſwade others to engage to fight and kill men, for a <hi>cauſe</hi> not rightly ſtated, or not throughly underſtood to be juſt, and of neceſſity to be maintained; for it is one of the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, unchriſtian, and unnaturall things that can enter into the mind or man, though it be to be feared that more then a few that have of late both in the Citie and Country, (and at preſent) are active to engage in killing and ſleying of men) cannot acquit themſelves of this abomination.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you, (you that are ſo forward and active to engage in the defence of the <hi>Kings, Presbyterian,</hi> or <hi>Independent intereſt,</hi> and yet know no juſt cauſe for either) conſider, was it ſufficient that the King at firſt invited you in generall termes to joyn with him, for the defence of the true <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> his own juſt <hi>Prerogatives,</hi> the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileages of Parliament,</hi> and the <hi>Liberty of the Subject;</hi> but never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in particular what that <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> was he would have defended, or what <hi>Prerogative</hi> would pleaſe him, what <hi>priviledges</hi> he would allow the Parliament, or what <hi>Freedoms</hi> the People?</p>
            <p>Or was it ſufficient thinke you now, that the Parliament invited you at firſt upon generall termes, to fight for the maintenance of the true <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> the <hi>Libertyes</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> and <hi>Priviledges</hi> of <hi>Parliament;</hi> when neither themſelves knew, for ought is yet ſeen, nor you, nor any body elſe, what they meant by the true <hi>Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> or what the <hi>Liberties of the People</hi> were, or what thoſe <hi>Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges</hi> of Parliament were, for which yet nevertheleſſe thouſands of men have been ſlain, and thouſands of Familyes deſtroyed?</p>
            <p>It is very like that ſome of you that joyned with the <hi>King</hi> upon his invitation, thought, that though the King had formerly countenanced Popery, and Superſtition,, had ſtretcht his Prerogative to the oppreſſion and deſtruction of his People, by <hi>Pattents, Projects, &amp;c.</hi> yet for the future he would have been more zealous for the truth, and more tender of his People, and not have perſiſted (notwithſtanding his new <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations</hi>) to maintain his <hi>old Principles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo likewiſe many of you that joyned with the Parliament, who had formerly ſeen, felt, or conſidered the perſecution of godly conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:162129:3"/>people by the Biſhops and their Cleargy, with the reproaches caſt upon them, and their grievous and deſtructive impriſonment, did beleeve the Parliament under the notion of <hi>Religion,</hi> intended to free the Nation from all compulſion in matters of Religion, and from mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, or perſecution for <hi>opinions,</hi> or <hi>non-conformity;</hi> and that all Lawes or Statutes tending thereunto ſhould have been repealed: But ſince you find (by killing and deſtroying their oppoſers) you have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled them to performe all things that might concern your freedome, or be conducible to the peace of the Kingdome. But do you now find that they do mean that, or the contrary? And will your conſciences give you leave any longer to fight or engage in the cauſe of <hi>Religion,</hi> when already you ſee what fruits you and your friends reap thereby.</p>
            <p>And no doubt many of you underſtood by the <hi>Liberties of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> that they intended to free the Commons in Parliament <hi>the peoples Repreſentative,</hi> ftom a <hi>Negative voyce,</hi> in <hi>King, or Lords,</hi> and would have declared themſelves the <hi>higheſt Authority,</hi> and ſo would have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to have removed the grievances of the Common-wealth: And when you had ſeen Pattents, Projects, and Shipmoney taken away, the <hi>High Commiſſion, and Starchamber</hi> aboliſhed, did you ever imagine to have ſeen men and women examined upon Interrogatories, and que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions againſt themſelves, and impriſoned for refuſing to anſwer? Or to have ſeen Commoners frequently ſentenced and impriſoned by the Lords? Did you ever dream that the oppreſſions of <hi>Committees</hi> would have exceeded thoſe of the <hi>Councel-table;</hi> or that in the place of <hi>Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents</hi> and <hi>Projects,</hi> you ſhould have ſeen an <hi>Exciſe</hi> eſtabliſhed, ten fold ſurpaſſing all thoſe, and <hi>Shipmoney</hi> together? You thought rather that <hi>Tythes</hi> would have been eſteem'd an oppreſſion, and that <hi>Trade</hi> would have been made perfectly free, and that <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> if continued, would have been abated, and not rayſed, for the ſupport of domineering facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and enrichment of foure or five great men, as they have been of late times, to the ſorrow and aſtoniſhment of all honeſt men, and the great prejudice of the Trade of the Nation.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſſe you hoped that both <hi>Lawes and Lawyers,</hi> and the <hi>procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in all Courts</hi> ſhould have been abreviated, and corrected, and that you ſhould never more have ſeen a Begger in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have ſeen the Common-wealth enſlaved for want of Parliaments, and alſo by their <hi>ſudden diſſolution,</hi> and you rejoyced that this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was not to be diſſolved by the <hi>King;</hi> but did you conceive it
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:162129:4"/>would have ſat ſeavn yeares <hi>to ſo little purpoſe,</hi> or that it ſhould ever have come to paſſe, to be eſteemed a crime to move for the ending there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? Was the perpetuating of this Parliament, and the <hi>oppreſſions</hi> they have brought upon you and yours, a part of that <hi>Liberty of the People</hi> you fought for? Or was it for ſuch a <hi>Priviledge of Parliament,</hi> that they only might have liberty to oppreſſe at their pleaſure, without any hope of remedy? If all theſe put together make not up the <hi>cauſe</hi> for which you fought, what was the <hi>Cauſe?</hi> What have ye obtained to the People, but theſe <hi>Libertyes,</hi> for they muſt not be called oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Theſe are the fruits of all thoſe vaſt disburſtments, and thoſe thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of lives that have been ſpent and deſtroyed in the late War.</p>
            <p>And though the <hi>Army</hi> ſeemed to be ſenſible of theſe groſſe juglings, and declared, and engaged againſt them, and profeſſed that they tooke not paines <hi>as a mercenary Army, hired to fight for the Arbitrary ends of a State,</hi> but in <hi>judgement</hi> and <hi>conſcience,</hi> for the preſervation of their own, and the Peoples <hi>juſt Rights and Libertyes:</hi> Yet when they had prevailed againſt thoſe their particular oppoſers, and accompliſhed the ends by them aymed at, all theſe things were forgotten, and thoſe perſons that appeared for the <hi>Peoples Freedoms,</hi> by them eſteemed and proceeded againſt as Mutineers, or Incendiaries.</p>
            <p>In like manner, the preſent <hi>Ruling Party of Presbyterians</hi> make a great ſhew of their apprehenſions of the great ſlavery and ſervitude brought upon the <hi>People,</hi> by the exerciſe or an <hi>Arbitrary power</hi> in the Parliament, and by the <hi>jurisdiction of the Sword</hi> in the hands of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my:</hi> They tell us that by this meanes the <hi>Trade</hi> of the Nation is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and that without the removall of theſe things, the peace of the Nation cannot be ſecured: And it is exceeding true: But I beſeech you conſider, whether they do not revive the ſame Play, and drive the ſame Deſigne, which was acted by the Parliament at firſt, and by the Army the laſt-Summer.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they cry out againſt the exerciſe of an arbitrary power in the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and yet labour to inveſt it in the <hi>King,</hi> nay challenge the exerciſe of it by themſelves: for what greater arbitrary power can there be in the world, then that a <hi>Prieſt</hi> or two, and a few Lay <hi>Elders,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of a <hi>Presbytery,</hi> ſhould have power to <hi>bind</hi> or <hi>looſe, bring in,</hi> or <hi>caſt out, ſave</hi> or <hi>deſtroy</hi> at their pleaſure, and enforce all perſons within the limits of their jurisdiction, to beleeve as they beleeve, and ſubmit to whatever they command, or elſe to be by them delivered o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to Sathan.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:162129:4"/>
            <p>Nay if you looke into thoſe of that party of the Magiſtracy of this City, that are the great promoters of the preſent worke: do there any men in the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld exerciſe a more arbitrary power? Do not many of them act only by the Rule of <hi>will and pleaſure,</hi> and have they not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly proſeſſed themſelves to be obliged to obſerve no other Rule then <hi>Diſcretion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though they decry agaitſt the power of the Sword in the hands of the <hi>Independents,</hi> yet do they not with all their might, labour to get it into the hands of the <hi>Presbyterians?</hi> and being there, will they not do that themſelves, which they complain of in others? will they not ſay that <hi>there are gain-ſayers whoſe mouthes muſt be ſtopt,</hi> and with the Sword rather then faile, and though <hi>Royal ſts</hi> or <hi>Independents</hi> may not uſe the Sword to enforce their <hi>Principles,</hi> yet Presbyterians may, as if all <hi>knowledge</hi> of <hi>the truth</hi> were centred in a <hi>Presbytery,</hi> conſiſting of halfe Scotch, halfe Engliſh, part Puritan, part Cavalier, luke-warm chriſtianity, neither hot nor cold zealous for the truth which they know not, only by heare-ſay, and only becauſe they love not <hi>Jndependency,</hi> that being to pure, nor <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> that being too prophane, they will be between both, (but not in a golden Meane, for that were well) but more zealons then either in outward performances, but for the power of godlines.— I ceaſe to judge, but we ſay we may know the <hi>tree</hi> by the <hi>fruit,</hi> and certain I am that <hi>Thiſtles</hi> never bore <hi>Figgs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if you ſhall examine what <hi>grounds of freedome</hi> they propoſe in all their Papers; what equall Rules of juſtice they offer to be inſiſted on as a ſure foundation for a laſting peace? Surely if you looke bur ſeriouſly into the bottom of their deſign, you will find that the peace they aime at is only their own; not the Nations, and that their own eaſe, honour and dominion, is the only thing they purſue, and ſo they could enjoy eaſe and plenty and ſtretch themſelves upon Beds of <hi>Down,</hi> they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver care what the poor Country ſhould ſuffer.</p>
            <p>To be ſhort, all the quarrell we have at this day in the Kingdome, is no other then a <hi>quarrel of Intereſts,</hi> and <hi>Partyes,</hi> a pulling down of one <hi>Tyrant,</hi> to ſet up another, and in ſtead of <hi>Liberty,</hi> heaping vpon our ſelves a greater ſlavery then that we fought againſt: certainly this is the Liberty that is ſo much ſtrove for, and for which there are ſuch freſh endeavours to engage men; but if you have not killed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed men enough for this, go on and deſtroy, kill and ſley, till your conſciences are ſwoln ſo full with the blood of the People, that they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:162129:5"/>burſtagen, and upon your death-beds may you ſee your ſelves the moſt horrid Murtherers that ever lived, ſince the time that <hi>Cain</hi> kild his brother without a juſt <hi>Cauſe;</hi> for where, or what is your <hi>cauſe?</hi> Beleeve it yee have a heavy reeckoning to make, and muſt undergo a ſad repentance, or it will go ill with you <hi>at the great day,</hi> when all the ſophiſtry of your great <hi>Reformers</hi> will ſerve you to little purpoſe, <hi>every man for himſelfe being to give an account for the things which he hath done in the body, whether they be good or evill:</hi> Then it will ſerve you to little purpoſe to ſay, the <hi>King, Parliament, Army, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents, Presbyterians,</hi> ſuch an <hi>Officer, Magiſtrate,</hi> or <hi>Miniſter</hi> deluded me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> no more then it did <hi>Adam,</hi> to ſay <hi>the woman whom thou gaveſt, &amp;c.</hi> It being thus decreed in heaven, <hi>the ſoule which ſinneth ſhall ſurely dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though what is paſt cannot be recalled, yet it muſt be repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, and ſpeciall care taken for the future, that you ſin no more in in this kind, and either ſtand ſtill or go right for the Future, to which end let theſe following directions be your guide.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You are to know, that a <hi>People living under a Government,</hi> as this Nation hath done, and doth, cannot lawfully put themſelves, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Arms, or engage in War to <hi>kill and ſley men,</hi> but upon a lawfull call and invitation <hi>from the Supream Authority,</hi> or <hi>Law-making power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the <hi>Supream Authority</hi> of this Nation were never yet ſo <hi>plainly declared,</hi> as that you underſtand certainly where it is, and who are inveſted therewith, <hi>you have then had no Warrant for what you have done,</hi> nor have any Plea in Law for your <hi>Indempnity,</hi> as ſome of all Parties have lately found to their coſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>And that this point of <hi>Supream Authority</hi> was ever certainly ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is abſolutely denyed; for according to the common ſuppoſition, it is 3. Eſtates, which till within theſe few yeares were ever taken to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 1. <hi>Lords Spirituall.</hi> 2. <hi>Lords Temporall.</hi> 3. <hi>The Commons in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament aſſembled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if theſe three were eſſentiall and equall, as all former Times ſeem to allow; How could the <hi>Lords Temporall</hi> and the <hi>Commons,</hi> caſt out the <hi>Lords Spirituall?</hi> For by the ſame rule, the <hi>Lords Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall,</hi> and <hi>Lords Temporall,</hi> might have <hi>caſt out the Commons,</hi> but the caſting out the <hi>Biſhops</hi> hath both anſwered the queſtion, and ended the controverſie.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:162129:5"/>
            <p>Since when the <hi>ſupream Authority</hi> is pretended to reſt in the <hi>King, Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons;</hi> and if ſo, when did the <hi>King</hi> aſſent to your Proceedings in this War, which all the art in the world will not perſwade him to be <hi>for him,</hi> but <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him,</hi> and to ruine him and his? Or when did the <hi>Parliament</hi> aſſent to the proceedings of you that joyned with the <hi>King</hi> in the late war pretendedly raiſed for the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Religion,</hi> the <hi>priviledges of Parliament,</hi> and <hi>Liberty of the Subject;</hi> and if the <hi>ſupream power</hi> reſide in all <hi>three, King, Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> how can the <hi>King</hi> juſtly do any thing without the conſent of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> or the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> without the <hi>King?</hi> May not the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> as juſtly proceed to make <hi>Laws, War</hi> or <hi>Peace,</hi> without the <hi>Commons</hi> as they without the <hi>King?</hi> If they are not <hi>equal,</hi> which of them are <hi>ſupream,</hi> and declared and proved by convincing reaſon ſo to be? If <hi>any</hi> that you are to <hi>obſerve?</hi> If <hi>none,</hi> what have you done? what can you lawfully do?</p>
            <p>That there ſhould be either <hi>three</hi> or <hi>two</hi> diſtinct Eſtates <hi>equally ſupream</hi> is an abſurd nullity in government, for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit <hi>two</hi> of them <hi>agree,</hi> and not the <hi>third,</hi> then there can be no proceedings or determination, and if there be but <hi>two,</hi> as is now pretended, in <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> whoſe Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have ſerved (how juſtly judge you) to <hi>make War</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcate mens eſtates:</hi> admit <hi>they</hi> agree not, then alſo nothing can be done, which in Government is ridiculous to imagine, beſides it is now a known caſe that <hi>their Ordinances</hi> are not <hi>pleadable</hi> againſt the <hi>Laws,</hi> and give no <hi>Indempnity,</hi> which were they the known <hi>ſupream Authority,</hi> could not but be effectual. That the <hi>King ſingle</hi> and <hi>alone</hi> is the <hi>ſupream Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> himſelf never pretended to it, claiming only a <hi>nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive voyce</hi> in the <hi>Law-making Power,</hi> by which rule nothing can be done without him, then which nothing is more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:162129:6"/>The <hi>Lords</hi> alſo never pretended to more then an <hi>equal ſhare</hi> with the <hi>Commons,</hi> which in effect is a <hi>nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive voyce</hi> and as unreasonable as in the <hi>King:</hi> And when the <hi>Commons</hi> have been by Petitioners ſtiled the <hi>ſupream au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> they have puniſhed the <hi>Petitioners,</hi> and diſclaimed the <hi>ſupream Authority:</hi> and as two years ſince, ſo very late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they have voted that the Kingdom ſhall be governed by <hi>King, Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons;</hi> which is a riddle that no man underſtands; for who knoweth what appertains to the <hi>King,</hi> what to the <hi>Lords,</hi> or what to the Houſe of <hi>Commons?</hi> It is all out as uncertain as at firſt; <hi>and if the trumpet give an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain ſound, who ſhall prepare himſelf for the battel?</hi> If by all your endeavors you cannot prevail to have the <hi>ſupream Authority declared and proved,</hi> how can you lawfully fight, or upon what grounds with a good conſcience can you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage your ſelves or perſwade others to engage in <hi>killing</hi> and <hi>ſlaying</hi> of <hi>men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if you ſhould have the <hi>ſupream Authority</hi> rationally proved and declared to be in the <hi>Commons</hi> diſtinct from any other, as being the <hi>ſole Repreſentative of the people;</hi> you muſt note that you are a <hi>free people,</hi> and are not to be <hi>preſſed</hi> or <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced</hi> to ſerve in Wars like horſes and bruit beaſts, but are to uſe the underſtanding God hath given you, <hi>in judging</hi> of the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> for defence whereof they deſire you to fight, for it is not ſufficient to fight by <hi>lawful authority,</hi> but you muſt be ſure to fight for what is <hi>just: Lawful authority</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſometimes miſtaken, and many times ſo perverted and corrupted, as to command the killing and impriſoning men for doing that which is <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>commendable,</hi> and for oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing what is <hi>unjuſt</hi> and <hi>deſtructive.</hi> Therefore as you are to forbear till you ſee the <hi>ſupream Authority</hi> diſtinctly and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally ſtated; ſo alſo you are not to engage till the <hi>Cauſe</hi> be expreſly declared, leſt after your next engagement you
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:162129:6"/>are as fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſeek of a <hi>juſt cauſe</hi> as <hi>now you are;</hi> and after you have prevailed in ſtead of finding your ſelves and your aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates <hi>freemen,</hi> you find your ſelves more enſlaved then you were formerly. For by experience you now find you may be made <hi>ſlaves as effectually</hi> by <hi>Parliament,</hi> as by any other kind of Government; why then perſiſt you to divide and fall into Factions? to <hi>kill and ſlay men</hi> for you <hi>know not what,</hi> to advance the <hi>honor and intereſt</hi> of you <hi>know not whom;</hi> the <hi>King, Parliament, great men</hi> in the <hi>City and Army</hi> can do nothing <hi>without you,</hi> to diſturb the <hi>Peace</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you therefore both <hi>Soldiers and People,</hi> who <hi>fight, pay</hi> and <hi>disburſe</hi> your <hi>eſtates,</hi> is to be charged all the evil that hath been done; if you on all hands had not been and were not ſo haſty to engage for the advancement or <hi>Intereſts</hi> to the prejudice of the <hi>Nation,</hi> it is very likely we had not only eſcaped thoſe late bloody turmoils that have happened a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, but alſo might prevent greater threatned dangers, which like an <hi>inundation</hi> begin to break in upon us: And if you now ſtop not, your <hi>Conſciences</hi> will be load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all that is to <hi>come,</hi> which threatneth far worſe then what is <hi>paſt;</hi> Therefore, if ye are either <hi>men</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> hold your hands till you know what you fight for, and be ſure that you have the <hi>truth of Freedom in it,</hi> or never medle, but deſiſt, and let who will both <hi>fight and pay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly there is none ſo vile, conſidering what hath been ſaid, that will again incur the guilt of <hi>murtherers,</hi> and fight before the <hi>Cauſe be plainly ſtated and publiſhed,</hi> and if that were done as it ought to be, poſſibly it may be attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without <hi>fighting,</hi> and might have been all this while, the difference not being ſo great as was imagined; Beſides, where is the man that would fight againſt the <hi>ſupream Authority,</hi> and a <hi>just Cauſe?</hi> and certainly there is none of you (whether <hi>Royalists, Presbyterians or Independents</hi>) ſo wicked as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:162129:7"/>to kill men without <hi>exceeding just grounds</hi> and upon the <hi>greateſt neceſsity,</hi> it being the ſaddeſt work in the world.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the preventing whereof, let us, I beſeech you, examine what <hi>good things</hi> there are <hi>wanting,</hi> that are eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential to the <hi>Peace, Freedom,</hi> and <hi>happineſs</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> that may not be obtained <hi>without fighting.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. Is there wanting the certain knowledg <hi>where the ſupream Authority is,</hi> and of <hi>right ought</hi> to be; It is confeſt no one thing is more wanting, nor can the <hi>Nation</hi> ever be quiet, or happy without it.</p>
               <p>But can it be any where <hi>juſtly</hi> and <hi>ſafely</hi> but in the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> who are choſen and truſted by the <hi>People?</hi> Certainly did men conſider that in oppoſing thereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they renounce and deſtroy their own freedoms, they would not do it for any thing in the world.</p>
               <p>If the conſideration of the manifold evils brought upon us by this Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> deter them, the next thing that is wanting is, <hi>That a ſet time be appointed for the ending of this Parliament,</hi> and a <hi>certainty</hi> for <hi>future Parliaments,</hi> both for their <hi>due elections, meeting,</hi> and <hi>diſſolving:</hi> And who will be ſo unreaſonable as to oppoſe any of theſe? cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the number cannot be conſiderable.</p>
               <p>Is it alſo neceſſary that <hi>That Parliaments be abridged the power of impreſsing men,</hi> to ſerve as bruit beaſts in the Wars, who will be againſt their being bounded therein? a <hi>good Cauſe</hi> never wanted <hi>men,</hi> nor an <hi>authority</hi> that had <hi>money</hi> to <hi>pay them.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:162129:7"/>
               <p>Hath it proved deſtructive in <hi>Parliaments</hi> to meddle in <hi>Religion,</hi> and to <hi>compel and reſtrain in matters of Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip?</hi> Are they evidently ſuch things as cannot be ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Judgment?</hi> Doth every man find it ſo that hath a <hi>living Conſcience?</hi> Who then will be againſt their binding here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, though they be entruſted to eſtabliſh an <hi>uncompulſive pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like way of worſhip for the Nation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is it unreaſonable that any perſon ſhould be exempt from thoſe proceedings of <hi>Law,</hi> unto which the generality of the <hi>People</hi> are to be <hi>ſubject?</hi> Who is there then that will not willingly have <hi>all</hi> from the <hi>higheſt</hi> to the <hi>loweſt</hi> bound alike?</p>
               <p>That Parliaments ſhould have no power to puniſh any perſon for doing that which is not againſt a <hi>known declared Law,</hi> or to take away <hi>general property,</hi> or to force men to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>queſtions againſt themſelves,</hi> or to order <hi>tryals,</hi> or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by any other ways then by <hi>twelve ſworn men,</hi> who would not rejoyce to have ſuch boundaries?</p>
               <p>Then, that the proceedings it <hi>Law</hi> might be <hi>rectified,</hi> and all <hi>Laws</hi> and the <hi>duty of Magiſtrates written and publiſhed in Engliſh:</hi> That the <hi>Exciſe</hi> might have a ſpeedy end, and no <hi>Taxes</hi> but by way of <hi>ſubſidies:</hi> That <hi>Trade</hi> might be <hi>free,</hi> and a leſs burthenſom way for the maintenance of <hi>Miniſters</hi> be eſtabliſhed, then that of <hi>Tythes;</hi> and that <hi>work</hi> and <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries</hi> be provided for all kind of <hi>poor people.</hi> Certainly for the obtaining of theſe things a man may juſtly adventure his <hi>life;</hi> all theſe being for a <hi>common good,</hi> and tend not to the ſetting up of any one <hi>party</hi> or <hi>faction</hi> of men.</p>
               <p>Theſe then are the <hi>Cauſes</hi> to be inſiſted on, or nothing: And if the <hi>ſupream Authority</hi> adhere to this <hi>Cauſe,</hi> they need neither fear <hi>Scotch, French,</hi> nor <hi>Engliſh Enemies;</hi> but if they decline this <hi>Cauſe,</hi> they are to be <hi>declined, the juſt freedom and happineſs of a Nation,</hi> being above all <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> whether of <hi>Kings, Parliaments,</hi> or <hi>any other.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:162129:8"/>
               <p>For ſhame therefore <hi>(Royaliſts, Presbyterians, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,)</hi> before you murther another man <hi>hold forth your Cauſe plainly and expreſly;</hi> and if any Adverſaries appear ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>within or without the Land, reaſon</hi> it out with them if it be poſſible deal as becometh <hi>Chriſtians, argue, perſwade,</hi> and uſe all poſſible means to prevent another <hi>War,</hi> and greater <hi>blood-ſhed;</hi> your <hi>great ones,</hi> [whether the <hi>King, Lords, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament men, rich Citizens, &amp;c.</hi> feel not the miſerable effects thereof, and ſo cannot be ſenſible; but you and your poor friends that depend on <hi>Farmes, Trades,</hi> and ſmall <hi>pay,</hi> have many an aking heart when theſe live in all <hi>pleaſure and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs:</hi> The accurſed thing is accepted by them, <hi>wealth</hi> and <hi>honor,</hi> and both comes by the bleeding miſerable diſtractions of the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and they fear an end of trouble would put an end to their glory and greatneſs.</p>
               <p>Oh therefore all you <hi>Soldiers</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> that have your <hi>Conſciences alive about you,</hi> put to your ſtrength of <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and all the might you have to prevent a further effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>blood;</hi> let not the <hi>covetous,</hi> the <hi>proud,</hi> the <hi>blood-thirſty man</hi> bear ſway amongſt you; fear not their high looks, give no ear to their <hi>charms,</hi> their <hi>promiſes</hi> or <hi>tears;</hi> they have no ſtrength without you, forſake them <hi>and ye will be strong for good,</hi> adhere to them, <hi>and they will be ſtrong to evil;</hi> for which <hi>you</hi> muſt <hi>anſwer,</hi> and give an <hi>account</hi> at the <hi>laſt day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>King, Parliament, great men</hi> in the <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Army,</hi> have made you but the <hi>ſtairs</hi> by which they have mounted to <hi>Honor, Wealth</hi> and <hi>Power.</hi> The only <hi>Quarrel</hi> that hath been, and at <hi>preſent is</hi> but this, namely, <hi>whoſe ſlaves the people ſhall be:</hi> All the <hi>power</hi> that any hath, was but a <hi>truſt</hi> convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from <hi>you</hi> to <hi>them,</hi> to be employed by <hi>them</hi> for <hi>your good;</hi> they have miſ-imployed their <hi>power,</hi> and inſtead of <hi>preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving you,</hi> have <hi>deſtroyed you:</hi> all <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> is <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted</hi> from the <hi>King</hi> to the <hi>Conſtable,</hi> and it is no other but
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:162129:8"/>the policy of <hi>Stateſmen</hi> to keep you divided by <hi>creating jealouſies</hi> and <hi>fears</hi> among you, to the end that their <hi>Tyranny</hi> and <hi>Injustice</hi> may paſs <hi>undiſcovered</hi> and <hi>unpuniſhed;</hi> but the <hi>peoples ſafety</hi> is <hi>the ſupream Law;</hi> and if a people muſt not be left without a means to preſerve it ſelf againſt the <hi>King,</hi> by the ſame rule they may preſerve themſelves againſt the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Army</hi> too; if they <hi>pervert</hi> the <hi>end</hi> for which they received their <hi>power,</hi> to wit <hi>the Nations ſafety;</hi> therefore ſpeedily <hi>unite</hi> your ſelves together, and as <hi>one man</hi> ſtand up for the defence of your <hi>Freedom,</hi> and for the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of ſuch <hi>equal rules of Government</hi> for the future, as ſhall lay a firm foundation of <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>happineſs</hi> to <hi>all the people without partiallity:</hi> Let <hi>Juſtice</hi> be your <hi>breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate,</hi> and you ſhall need to fear no enemies, for you ſhall ſtrike a terrour to your now <hi>inſulting oppreſſors,</hi> and force all the <hi>Nations Peace</hi> to fly before <hi>you.</hi> Proſecute and proſper. <hi>Vale.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:162129:9"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>CAn there be a more bloody Project then to engage men to kill one another, and yet no juſt cauſe declared? Therefore I adviſe all men that would be eſteemed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or Rational, really to conſider what may be done for the future that is conducible to the Peace of the Nation; If the Peace of the Nation cannot be ſecured without the Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the King, let it be done ſpeedily and honorably, and provide againſt his miſgovernment for the future; let his power be declared and limited by Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If the</hi> Peace <hi>of the</hi> Nation <hi>cannot be ſecured by the</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance <hi>of this</hi> Parliament, <hi>let a</hi> Period <hi>be ſet for the</hi> diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>thereof, but firſt make certain proviſion for the ſucceſsive</hi> calling, electing <hi>and</hi> ſitting <hi>of Parliaments for the future; let their</hi> Priviledges <hi>be</hi> declared <hi>and</hi> power limitted, <hi>as to what they are empowred and what not; for doubtleſs in Parliaments rightly conſtituted conſiſts the</hi> Freedom <hi>of a</hi> Nation: <hi>And in all things do as you would be done unto, ſeek peace with all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But above all things, abandon your former actings for a <hi>King</hi> againſt a <hi>Parliament,</hi> or an <hi>Army</hi> againſt both; for the Presbyterians againſt the Independents, &amp;c. for in ſo doing you do but put a Sword into your enemies hands to deſtroy you, for hitherto, which of them ſoever were in power, they plaid the Tyrants and oppreſſed, and ſo it will ever be, when <hi>Parties</hi> are ſupported: Therefore if you engage at all, do it by <hi>Lawfull</hi> Authority, let your <hi>Cauſe</hi> be declared, and <hi>juſt</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo and let it be for the good of the whole Nation, without which you will not only hazard being Slaves, but alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract upon your ſelves, and Poſterities the guilt of Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers. <hi>vale.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
